https://jesscs.github.io/

#### **SUMMARY**

Senior UX Researcher specialized in human-computer interaction (HCI) and health informatics. Extensive experience in multidisciplinary research, including conducting *formative studies* to identify needs and opportunities; *iterative design and development* of novel methods and tools to support those needs; and *evaluations* to examine feasibility and develop design implications for future tools.

#### **EDUCATION**

## University of Washington (9/2014—9/2020)

Seattle, WA

Ph.D., Computer Science & Engineering

Dissertation: Goal-Directed Self-Tracking in the Management of Chronic Health Conditions

Advisors: James Fogarty, Sean Munson

M.S. earned December 2016

GPA: 3.9

# Pomona College (8/2010—5/2014)

Claremont, CA

Computer Science Major, Neuroscience Experience

GPA: 3.9

# University of Edinburgh (8/2012—12/2012)

Edinburgh, Scotland

GPA: 3.9

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior UX Researcher (May 2024—Present)

Google

UX Researcher (June 2022— May 2024)

Conducts research studies to inform and evaluate driving navigation in Google Maps.

## Senior Research Scientist (September 2021—May 2022)

**Evidation Health** 

#### Research Scientist (March 2020—August 2021)

Collaboratively designed, conducted, and analyzed novel quantitative and mixed-methods studies to investigate health-related perspectives and behaviors and examine novel technologies, tailoring study design to project goals (e.g., market research, patient-centered design, randomized control trials).

Developed study design and documents (e.g., protocols, informed consent forms, surveys, interviews).

Consulted with internal and external stakeholders to elicit and communicate goals and constraints.

## Research Assistant (September 2014—September 2020)

**University of Washington** 

Investigated supporting people and their health providers in collecting, analyzing, and interpreting patient-generated data to meet personalized health goals in multiple health contexts.

Built interactive, exploratory visualizations to help people identify personal IBS triggers.

Conducted surveys and interviews to characterize needs and opportunities in migraine tracking.

Proposed goal-directed self-tracking as a general framework for self-tracking data.

Collaborated with health providers in the design and evaluation of novel prototype health apps.

Research resulted in related grants from the NSF (\$500k) and the NIH (\$1.5M).

More detailed descriptions available on my personal website.

## Research Intern (Summer 2017)

**Microsoft Research** 

Conducted a feasibility study to investigate how a mobile app can support behavioral therapy.

Designed and analyzed surveys to: 1) characterize significant positive changes in anxiety, depression, and coping skill use; 2) develop a theoretical model to describe how the app supported these improvements; and 3) distill design implications for future tools.

Identified opportunities for machine learning techniques to provide personalized and context-aware suggestions to help people identify feasible and useful positive coping skills.

## Project Manager (August 2013—May 2014)

**Harvey Mudd Clinic** 

Led development of a web app to provide personalized vacation recommendations for Expedia, Inc.

## **Undergraduate Research Assistant (Sumer 2013)**

**Carnegie Mellon HCII** 

Investigated augmentations of a chronic illness forum to help people find credible information.

#### Research Intern (Summers 2011 and 2012)

**Stanford School of Medicine** 

Ran wet lab experiments at the Conte Center for Neuroscience Research.

## **Undergraduate Research Assistant (Spring of 2012)**

**Pomona College** 

Developed a web application to identify fusion genes, which have implications in cancer.

#### **AWARDS/HONORS**

Best Paper Honorable Mention, ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems (2018)

Best Paper Award, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (2017)

Best Paper Honorable Mention, ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (2017)

NSF GRFP Awardee (2016)

Marilyn Fries Endowed Regental Fellowship Recipient (2014)

ARCS Foundation Fellow (2014)

Harvey Mudd Computer Science Clinic Team Award Winner (2014

Pomona College Marshall and Rhodes Scholarship Nominee (2013)

Six-Time Pomona College Scholar (2010-2013)

Grace Hopper Scholarship Recipient (2013)

DREU-CRAW Participant (2013)

National Merit Scholar (2010)

#### **SKILLS**

User research: semi-structured interviews, surveys, field studies, observation, contextual inquiry

Data analysis: qualitative data analysis (e.g., coding, thematic analysis, affinity diagraming;

quantitative data analysis (e.g., with R, Python, Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn)

*Prototyping:* prototypes, mobile and web app development (e.g., in Angular, Ionic, D3.js)

Leadership: project management; communication (e.g., scientific and technical writing,

presentations); diversity and inclusion advocacy.

## **PUBLICATIONS**

Full publication lists available on my personal website and my Google Scholar Page.

Jong Ho Lee, **Jessica Schroeder**, Daniel A. Epstein (2021). <u>Understanding and Supporting Self-Tracking App Selection</u>. *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT 2021)*. https://doi.org/10.1145/3494980

Susanne Kirchner, **Jessica Schroeder**, James Fogarty, Sean A. Munson (2021). <u>"They don't always think about that"</u>: <u>Translational Needs in the Design of Personal Health Informatics Applications.</u> *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2021)*. https://doi.org/10.1145/3411764.3445587

Sean A. Munson, **Jessica Schroeder**, Ravi Karkar, Julie A. Kientz, Chia-Fang Chung, James Fogarty (2020). <u>The Importance of Starting with Goals in N-of-1 Studies</u>. *Frontiers Digital Health 2020*. https://doi.org/10.3389/fdgth.2020.00003

Jessica Schroeder, Jina Suh, Chelsey Wilks, Mary Czerwinski, Sean A. Munson, James Fogarty, Tim Althoff (2020). <u>Data-Driven Implications for Translating Evidence-Based Psychotherapies into Technology-Delivered Interventions</u>. *Proceedings of the International Conference on Pervasive Computing Technologies for Healthcare (PervasiveHealth 2020)*. https://doi.org/10.1145/3421937.3421975

**Jessica Schroeder,** Ravi Karkar, Natalia Murinova, James Fogarty, Sean A. Munson (2020). <u>Examining Opportunities for Goal-Directed Self-Tracking to Support Chronic Condition Management.</u> *Proceedings of the ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing* (*UbiComp 2020*). https://doi.org/10.1145/3369809

Chia-Fang Chung, Qiaosi Wang, **Jessica Schroeder**, Allison Cole, Jasmine Zia, James Fogarty, Sean A. Munson (2019). <u>Identifying and Planning for Individualized Change: Patient-Provider Collaboration Using Lightweight Food Diaries in Healthy Eating and Irritable Bowel Syndrome.</u> *Proceedings of the ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp 2019)*. https://doi.org/10.1145/3314394

**Jessica Schroeder**, Ravi Karkar, James Fogarty, Julie A. Kientz, Sean A. Munson, Matthew Kay (2018). <u>A Patient-Centered Proposal for Bayesian Analysis of Self-Experiments for Health</u>. *Journal of Healthcare Informatics Research*. http://doi.org/10.1007/s41666-018-0033-x

Jessica Schroeder, Chia-Fang Chung, Daniel A. Epstein, Ravi Karkar, Adele Parsons, Natalia Murinova, James Fogarty, Sean A. Munson (2018). Examining Self-Tracking by People with Migraine: Goals, Needs, and Opportunities in a Chronic Health Condition. Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems (DIS 2018). Best Paper Honorable Mention. https://doi.org/10.1145/3196709.3196738

**Jessica Schroeder**, Chelsey Wilks, Kael Rowan, Arturo Toledo, Ann Paradiso, Mary Czerwinski, Gloria Mark, Marsha M. Linehan (2018). <u>Pocket Skills: A Conversational Mobile Web App To Support Dialectical Behavioral Therapy</u>. *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2018)*. https://doi.org/10.1145/3173574.3173972

Ravi Karkar, **Jessica Schroeder**, Daniel Epstein, Laura Pina, Jeffrey Scofield, James Fogarty, Julie Kientz, Sean Munson, Roger Vilardaga, Jasmine Zia (2017). <u>TummyTrials: A Feasibility Study of Using Self-Experimentation to Detect Individualized Food Triggers</u>. *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2017)*. Best Paper Honorable Mention. https://doi.org/10.1145/3025453.3025480

Chia-Fang Chung, Elena Agapie, **Jessica Schroeder**, Sonali Mishra, James Fogarty, Sean Munson (2017). When Personal Tracking Becomes Social: Examining the Use of Instagram for Healthy Eating. *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2017)*. https://doi.org/10.1145/3025453.3025747

Daniel Epstein, Nicole Lee, Jennifer Kang, Elena Agapie, **Jessica Schroeder**, Laura Pina, James Fogarty, Julie Kientz, Sean Munson (2017). <u>Examining Menstrual Tracking to Inform the Design of Personal Informatics Tools</u>. *Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2017)*. Best Paper Awardee. https://doi.org/10.1145/3025453.3025635

**Jessica Schroeder**, Jane Hoffswell, Chia-Fang Chung, James Fogarty, Sean Munson, Jasmine Zia (2017). Supporting Patient-Provider Collaboration to Identify Individual Triggers using Food and Symptom Journals. Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW 2017). http://doi.org/10.1145/2998181.2998276

Jasmine Zia, Chia-Fang Chung, **Jessica Schroeder**, Sean Munson, Julie Kientz, James Fogarty, Elizabeth Bales, Jeanette Schenk, Margaret Heitkemper (2016). <u>The Feasibility, Usability, and Perceived Clinical Utility of Traditional Paper Food and Symptom Journals for Patients with Irritable Bowel Syndrome</u>. *Neurogastroenterology and Motility*. http://doi.org/10.1111/nmo.12935

Jasmine Zia, **Jessica Schroeder**, Sean Munson, James Fogarty, Linda Nguyen, Pamela Barney, Margaret Heitkemper, Uri Ladabaum (2016). <u>Feasibility and Usability Pilot Study of a Novel Irritable Bowel Syndrome Food and Gastrointestinal Symptom Journal Smartphone App</u>. *Clinical and Translational Gastroenterology*. http://doi.org/10.1038/ctg.2016.9

Jamie L. Crawford, Cheng Guo, **Jessica Schroeder**, Rosa I. Arriaga, Jennifer Mankoff (2014). <u>Is it a Question of Trust?</u>: <u>How Search Preferences Influence Forum Use</u>. *PervasiveHealth 2014*. 118-125. http://doi.org/10.4108/icst.pervasivehealth.2014.254988

Federica Sarti, Zhenjie Zhang, **Jessica Schroeder**, Lu Chen (2013). <u>Rapid Suppression of Inhibitory Synaptic Transmission by Retinoic Acid</u>. *Journal of Neuroscience*, 33(28): 11440-11450. http://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1710-13.2013

Federica Sarti, **Jessica Schroeder**, Jason Aoto, Lu Chen (2012). <u>Conditional RARa Knockout Mice Reveal Acute Requirement for Retionic Acid and RARa in Homeostatic Plasticity</u>. *Frontiers in Molecular Neuroscience*, 5(16). http://doi.org/10.3389/fnmol.2012.00016

#### SELECT WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

<u>Personalizing Health Technologies to Support Patient and Provider Goals</u>. **Jessica Schroeder**, James Fogarty, Sean A. Munson. *Identifying Challenges and Opportunities in Human–AI Collaboration in Healthcare* (CSCW 2019).

Examining Self-Tracking by People with Migraine: Goals, Needs, and Opportunities in a Chronic Health Condition. Jessica Schroeder, Chia-Fang Chung, Daniel A. Epstein, Ravi Karkar, Adele Parsons, Natalia Murinova, James Fogarty, Sean A. Munson. Workshop on Interactive Systems in Healthcare (CHI 2019).

Mobile Health and Personal Informatics in Mental Health and Migraine. **Jessica Schroeder**. *Symposium on Computing and Mental Health* (CHI 2018).

Needs, Challenges, and Opportunities in Long-Term Tracking to Support Migraine Management. **Jessica Schroeder**, Natalia Murinova, James Fogarty, Sean Munson. *A Short Workshop on Next Steps Towards Long Term Self Tracking* (CHI 2018).

Supporting Patient-Provider Collaboration to Identify Individual Triggers using Food and Symptom Journals. Jessica Schroeder, Jane Hoffswell, Chia-Fang Chung, James Fogarty, Sean Munson, Jasmine Zia. *Workshop on Interactive Systems in Healthcare* (CHI 2017).

Supporting Patient-Provider Communication and Relationships with Personal Informatics Data. Chia-Fang Chung, **Jessica Schroeder**, Jasmine Zia, James Fogarty, Julie A. Kientz, Sean A. Munson. *Workshop on Quantified Data and Social Relationships* (CHI 2017).

<u>Hypothesis Formation and Hypothesis Testing: Design Challenges in Self-Experimentation</u>. Ravi Karkar, **Jessica Schroeder**, James Fogarty, Julie A. Kientz, Sean A. Munson, Jasmine Zia. *Digital Health & Self-Experimentation Workshop* (CHI 2017).

Exploring New Design Directions for Menstrual Tracking Technology. Daniel A. Epstein, Nicole B. Lee, Jennifer H. Kang, Elena Agapie, **Jessica Schroeder**, Laura R. Pina, James Fogarty, Julie A. Kientz, Sean A. Munson. *Hacking Women's Health* (CHI 2017).

Using Personal Data in Everyday Life: Self-Experimentation in Personalized Health. Ravi Karkar, **Jessica Schroeder**, Jasmine Zia, Roger Vilardaga, James Fogarty, Sean A. Munson, Julie A. Kientz. *Symposium on Use of Patient-Generated Data Beyond Self-Regulation* (ISRII 2016).

The Feasibility, Usability, and Perceived Clinical Utility of Traditional Paper Food and Symptom Journals for Patients with Irritable Bowel Syndrome. Jasmine Zia, Chia-Fang Chung, **Jessica Schroeder**, Jeanette Schenk, Sean A. Munson, Julie A. Kientz, James Fogarty, Margaret Heitkemper. *The Federation of Neurogastroenterology & Motility*.

#### **TALKS**

Supporting Patient-Provider Collaboration to Identify Individual Triggers Using Food and Symptom Journals. Session: Human Computer Interaction and Self-Tracking. *University of Washington Computer Science & Engineering Affiliates*. October 2016.

#### **POSTERS**

Developing a Patient-Centered Digital Intervention for Increasing Influenza Vaccination Rates in People with Cardiovascular Disease using a Remote Mixed-Methods Approach. *ESWI* 2001.

Examining Self-Tracking by People with Migraine: Goals, Needs, and Opportunities in a Chronic Health Condition. *University of Washington Computer Science & Engineering Affiliates* 2017.

Supporting Patient-Provider Collaboration to Identify Individual Triggers Using Food and Symptom Journals. *University of Washington Computer Science & Engineering Affiliates* 2016.

Personal Guidance on Individualized Food Triggers for IBS Patients. *University of Washington Computer Science & Engineering Affiliates* 2015.

Personal Guidance on Individualized Food Triggers for IBS Patients. *Intel Science and Technology Center for Pervasive Computing Retreat* 2015.

#### **TEACHING**

## Teaching Assistant, CSE 510: Advanced Topics in HCI (Winter 2018, Fall 2018)

Designed and graded assignments, critiqued projects, and advised students. (*Professor: James Fogarty*)

# Writing Fellow, Pomona Writing Center (August 2011—May 2014)

Appointed position to help students improve papers (e.g., essays, personal statements, lab reports). As Senior Science Writing Fellow in 2013/2014, I led improvements in scientific writing support.

## SERVICE, MENTORING, AND LEADERSHIP

Affiliate Assistant Professor, UW Computer Science & Engineering (August 2021—Present)

Volunteer position enabling ongoing mentorship and research collaboration.

# Research Mentorship (June 2020—Present)

Mentorship has included interns at Evidation Health as well as HCI students from UW and UCI.

#### HCI Seminar Lead, UW Computer Science & Engineering (January 2017—June 2018)

Led improvements to the seminar and organized quarterly themes, presentations, and feedback.

#### Reviewer (Fall 2016—Present)

ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2017--2021), ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW 2018, 2019, & 2021), ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems (DIS 2018 & 2019), International Conference on Affective Computing and Intelligent Interaction (ASCII 2021), and PACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT 2020).

## HCI Visit Days Coordinator, UW Computer Science & Engineering (Winter 2018)

Coordinated one-on-ones with faculty and current grad students; organized afternoon activity.

# Graduate Student Admissions Volunteer, UW Computer Science & Engineering (Fall 2016)

Reviewed graduate student applications to advise on admissions.

# New Graduate Orientation Leader, UW Computer Science & Engineering (Fall 2015)

Organized orientation for the new computer science graduate students at the University of Washington. Coordinated talks from student organizations, grad students, and professors.

# Class Representative, University of Edinburgh Informatics Department (Fall 2012)

Acted as a liaison between faculty and students to help voice complaints and deliver suggestions.

## **Volunteer, Miscellaneous Organizations (Fall 2008—Present)**

Volunteer with Equality California/the Human Rights Campaign, Organization for Special Needs Families, Pomona College Draper Center, and AmeriCorps Jumpstart Little Readers Program. My recent volunteering focuses on outreach to people—particularly girls and young women—considering pursuing computer science or other STEM fields, including discussing STEM research with girls ages 6-18 and their parents at a Go, Girl, Go! event, working at UW computer science grad recruitment booths at Hopperx1 Seattle and the Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing, and visiting the Pomona College Computer Science Department to talk to undergraduates considering graduate school.